Last week, I reacted to Jeff Nippert's
tiered list of glute exercises, and this
week, I'm reacting to Athleen X's tiered
list of glute exercises. Now, this is
two years old, but it's great content.
It's really good to hear other people's
thoughts, and then for me to share my
thoughts on top of that. So, in case you
don't know Athleen X, he has 14 million
followers on YouTube. That's got to be
more than any other fitness YouTuber,
right? I can't think of anyone who even
comes close to be honest. So very
influential guy, but glutes are my jam.
So let's get down to it. And so even a
high foot placement doesn't save this
exercise's placement at the bottom of my
list. Mike press has got to
go. What's up guys? Jeff Cavalere,
athletics.com. What you see behind me is
a bunch of different leg exercises
specifically for the hamstrings and
glutes. And they share a lot of
functions together. So, we're going to
group them together. But not just that.
I want to help you to find the ones that
are actually worth your time. Cuz we're
going to do what we always do here.
We're going to rank them from the best
to the worst, leaving you only with the
best exercises capable of delivering the
gains that you're after. All right. So,
as always, guys, in our exercises rank
series, we have to define the criteria
for the inclusion of these exercises in
this list. Number one, they have to be
capable of being progressively
overloaded. Can you continue to increase
the resistance to keep those gains
coming? Number two, can you do these
exercises and create muscle growth and
hypertrophy as the main focus? Sure,
there are strength exercises, but for
this list, they have to create muscle
growth. And number three, guys, as a
physical therapist, as always, each of
these exercises has to have one thing in
common. They all have to be done by me.
Oh god. Where have you been? I've been
hanging out in the back. Where have you
been? Why do you have to do the
exercises? Oh, I'm the one with the
juicy booty, remember? Oh, I wish you'd
stay away. Listen, they all have to be
safe. And by being safe, what I'm
talking about is they can't compromise
pain in order to deliver the gains that
we're after here, guys. So each of these
exercises is going to fit that important
criteria. And so as always, we're going
to start here at the bottom of the list
in the worst category and work our way
up. And as I mentioned in the open here,
the hamstrings and glutes actually do
share some functions together. Both of
them are capable of extending the hip or
bringing the leg straight back behind
the body. But the hamstrings also have
the capability of bending the knee. So,
one of the worst ways to do this,
unfortunately, is one of the most
popular exercises and ways to do it.
It's the prone hamstring curl. But
before you get too excited, trust me,
there's going to be better options
ahead. The reason why I don't like this
particular version of the exercise is
because of the position being face down.
And as you struggle to get that weight
up and really try to get your feet into
that end position, we oftentimes will
drive our thighs down into the pad that
engages the hip flexors, which as we
know attach to the lumbar vertebrae,
which can start to pull on them and
result in low back pain or spasm. Not
the way we want to really try to build
our hamstrings. Now, as I mentioned, the
exercise does fit the criteria of
hypertrophy and overload. But again,
knowing that there's better options
ahead, I'm not willing to take that
trade-off. So, for me, it's going to
start at the bottom of the barrel with a
big red X. Next, you know, the prone
hamstring curl, the lying leg curl, I
love that exercise. I always liked it
more than seated leg curls, but a recent
study was published showing that seated
leg curls led to greater hamstring
growth than lying leg curls, but it was
on beginners. And the researcher, Ma, he
never disclosed the type of equipment he
used. I like to look into that. I looked
into it. I couldn't find I believe it
was the lying leg crow. I couldn't find
a picture of it or maybe it was a sea
leg curl, but I don't know what
equipment they use. This group of
researchers never includes pictures,
images, videos, and it's annoying cuz
you want to see how it was done. And a
lot of the research published on
lengthen training is by this group MAU.
And what if they don't even know how to
lift? Who would know? Some of these
younger researchers, Plotkin, Milo Wolf,
PAC. This is the new wave of
researchers. They're including pictures.
They're including videos of their
subjects. So, there are no doubts as to
how the exercise were performed. But
talking about lying leg curls, a lot of
those machines are flexed. They have you
significantly bent at the hips and Jeff
looks at things from a lens of a
physical therapist. So, he's looking at
safety. And we always think of anterior
pelvic tilt as being a bad thing. But
think about it. When you're in anterior
pelvic tilt, what happens? The
hamstrings get longer. You increase
their length. So, if it doesn't cause
pain, I have no problem with
purposefully anterior pelvic tilting to
get a better stretch on the hammies. You
can also purposely flex the hips more or
or buy a leg curl machine that has more
hip flexion in it and then you make it
more like a seated leg curl. But if you
have a seated leg curl, then don't try
to make them the same. Train the
different lengths. Have a glute exercise
and this one you've probably seen before
or done and it's just a simple heel
press. Now this is a body weight
exercise easily done. No equipment
limitations here to get in the way.
However, it still doesn't make it very
high up my list. Why? Well, it's very
much incapable of the overload that we
seek in order to build muscle. You're
doing mostly a body weight movement
here. And it's also very limited in its
range of motion. Even when it's done
correctly here, you're talking about a
very limited 10 to 15 degrees of motion
for the entire exercise. And even more
than that, it's often times
misperformed. Because this is one of
those exercises that easily leads itself
to muscle substitution as we start to
rotate the hips, taking away some of the
effort from the glute max. Guys, this is
definitely one that belongs here at the
bottom and it's not going to I mean, no
one even does that exercise. That's like
a warm up. So, yeah, who cares about
that? I wish Jeff did this more recently
to get his take on like all the modern
exercises that have blown up on, you
know, Instagram, Tik Tok, etc. lately
because he'd undoubtedly have a whole
new list to deliver the gains that
you're looking for. So, between the last
exercise and this one, I kind of feel
like I'm pissing off a lot of people in
my audience and a lot of females, but it
has to be said and I'm trying to deliver
you the best information. And that
exercise that has to go next is the
stepmill. And you guys have probably
seen this and maybe even seen the people
who, you know, add that little flare of
the hip extension at the end. It still
doesn't save the exercise. Why? Well, a
lot of times these stepmills are
actually powered, which means that as
you step, the motor on the machine
brings your leg back down into
extension, not the muscles in your body.
That's a problem. What makes this worse
is the only muscles that are working are
your hip flexors once again just to lift
your foot up onto the next step only to
take that ride back down. It's not going
to get you where. And I've heard that
with treadmills, too, that like the belt
pulls your leg down and you just have to
lift your legs up, but no, that's not
true. I don't agree with that from a
physics standpoint. Like, yes, the steps
are descending, but think if you had a
giant escalator and you're running to
the top, you're aren't just going to use
your hip flexors the whole time. You
have to power your way up the entire
thing. I don't think it changes the
muscle activity that much. Whether
you're doing it in real life, like
climbing stairs versus using the
stepmills, same with sprinting on a
treadmill versus sprinting over ground,
it doesn't do the work for you and
you're just using hip flexors to lift
the legs up. want to be and it could
lead to some of that back pain we talked
about. Now, sometimes you'll be lucky
enough to find a version of the machine
that you actually power by driving your
foot down into extension, but at the end
of the day, any exercise that could be
done for many, many, many minutes in a
row becomes less anorobic and therefore
less likely to deliver muscle gains and
more aerobic. Totally agree. At the end
of the day, it's cardio. Cardio does not
build muscle like weights do. It doesn't
fit our categories or criteria here and
therefore it also is going to get a big
red X. And so if my ladies out there got
maybe a little bit mad at me, this time
I'm going to give everyone a chance to
because the next exercise on this list
is the leg press. Now look, I understand
a lot of people have used the leg press
as an alternative to a squat, especially
if they have knee pains and problems and
maybe even had seen some gains along the
way. My issue is as a glute developer,
it's a horrible exercise. There's no way
around it. And I know people say, "Well,
Jeff, that's maybe because you're doing
it incorrectly. You need to put your
feet high up on the platform in order to
get more glutes and hamstrings." It
doesn't save the exercise, guys. And
here's why. First of all, when we put
our feet high up on the plate, what we
get is a lot of hip flexion. A lot of
hip flexion. Actually, you may not be
able to see it until I take the position
at the bottom and I simply turn it to a
standing position as you would at the
bottom of a squat. And there's no squat
you've done that's ever looked like this
for good reason, cuz it's not a great
way to do a squat. With this amount of
hip flexion, what oftentimes happens is
you get an extreme amount of posterior
tilt and lumbar flexion that can
compromise the stability of the low back
and the SI joint. Two things we don't
want to do. But more than that, when we
go back and we extend our legs, look at
the excursion we go through. What is the
range of motion on the exercise? All
right. So, in Jeff's defense, a lot of
this research didn't exist a couple
years ago, but the leg press done this
way is actually theoretically an amazing
glute exercise. Well, first off, we
actually have a couple of published
studies showing good glute growth with
leg press. So, it's not theoretical at
this point. It's been tested. So, leg
presses do grow the glutes. Now, I used
to agree with Jeff because I tested the
EMG on myself, but I think maybe I was
sitting on the electrodes or something
because I got such low glute activity
with the leg press. However, our study
from 2023, Plotkin Edall 2023, showed
the EMG did not predict muscle growth.
And the reason why with the glutes is
because when you stretch a muscle to
long lengths, for some reason the glutes
shut down. They don't activate that
high. They don't electrically activate
that high in the stretch. But stretching
can grow muscle and activating a muscle
can grow muscle. So kind of two pathways
there. So EMG predicts the active
component of muscle force and then
length change or excursion predicts the
passive element or the passive muscle
force part of the equation. But the leg
press is a length and partial. And then
Jeff says, "You would never squat this
way." That actually would be the most
glute dominant squat possible, just
totally bent over like that. When you
have that kind of like your knee being
right here into your chest, that
maximally stretches the lower glute max.
And then you drive it forward. Yes, it's
not moving through a large range of
motion, but it's a lengthened partial.
You might move out to where you're at a
90° angle, and then you look at that's
when a hip thrust starts. Then the hip
thrust takes you from that 90° to full
hip hyperextension. So in theory, leg
presses and hip thrust would perfectly
complement each other. Train the whole
length, but you can never get your all
out of one exercise. One exercise
doesn't do it all. So the way I see it,
leg presses are freaking great for
training the glutes in a lengthened
position. Single leg leg presses, double
leg leg presses done with a high foot
position. They're way better, way more
torque at the hips, less torque on the
knees. You can even go sumo if you want.
If you go narrower, it's a little more
stretch. Wider, maybe more activation.
But I love leg presses. I used to not.
I've changed my mind over the years.
Maybe Jeff's changed his mind a little
bit. But he does accurately mention that
some people get injured from leg presses
and it's because of that posterior
pelvic tilt, that buttwink in deep hip
flexion. You got to figure that out. You
got to learn how to avoid that because
I've seen a lot of really bad injuries
on the leg press. In fact, in 2006, my
business partner had to be ambulanced
out of the gym. He had to be taken away
on a stretcher. He messed up his low
back so bad he couldn't even walk out of
the gym. So yeah, leg presses can be
dangerous if you don't know what you're
doing. So you got to learn that aspect,
but once you master that aspect, you
don't have to worry about it. You know
how to keep your lumbar in check. You
can get that high foot placement, make
it super, super glute dominant. You
almost want your shin being
perpendicular to your torso at the
bottom position. Remember, hip extension
is what we're looking for when we're
trying to train the glutes. We've gone
through very little hip extension. went
from extremely flexed to moderately
flexed, but still never even close to
neutral, let alone extended. The
exercise does not do a good job of
targeting the glutes. Therefore, it's
going to stay here at the bottom of the
list with the big red X right through
it. And so, with that, now I get to
break out my blue marker as we head up
the charts here into the better
category. And for this, we need to go
back and look at the same position we
just talked about with the leg press.
It's the dumbbell reverse sprinter
lunge. And yes, you might notice that
same chest to thigh position, but
there's some very different things going
on here. Number one, with that one leg
left behind us, we're actually
neutralizing the pelvis a little bit and
relieving some of that excessive
posterior tilt, which makes this
exercise a lot safer. But more
importantly, in terms of the
effectiveness of it, we're overloading
that hip extension. We're getting not
into that abbreviated range we saw in
the leg press, but we're able to
overload it through much more active hip
extension. This is one of my favorite
ways to do the movement. And for those
of you who I mentioned that had knee
pain on squats, this is going to give
you a chance to relieve yourself of a
lot of that pain and still get the gains
that you were looking for in the first
place. So for me, it gets the first blue
circle. I've never heard them called
sprinter lunges before. But yeah, I
agree with everything he said about
those. You just don't see those very
often, but theoretically those are a
great glute exercise. It's kind of like
an exercise I talked about called the
Romanian Bulgarian where you kind of
combine a single leg RDL with a
Bulgarian split squat. Same concept.
You're taking a reverse lunge. you're
involving more range of motion and
you're making it less quad dominant and
more hip dominant. So, agree with that
in the better category. Next up in the
better category is one of those step ups
from the exercises that were in the
worst category. And if you're going to
do those heel presses, you might as well
do instead a standing cuff kickback. And
this is where you take one of those
cuffs and put it around your ankle and
just kick back against resistance. And
that's the key against resistance.
Because what was lacking in that first
exercise, as you remember, was the
overload and resistance capable of
creating any type of muscle growth.
Well, here we can get that. And more
importantly, while it may still
encourage some of those muscle
substitutions that we talked about with
the heel press before, being on your
feet propriceptively allows you to move
your leg back easier in a straighter
line. So, while it's still a small range
of motion, it's one that you can perform
more effectively and easily. And as I
said, overloaded, it gets the next up in
the better category with the Okay, so
yeah, cable kickbacks. There's so many
ways to do them. Those ones he showed
very stable. He's holding on. I love
them. We do them at the end of the
workout because they don't fit into any
category. It's not a squat lunge. It's
not a thrust bridge. It technically is a
hinge, but you don't want that to be
your main hinge exercise. You want your
hinge to be a type of deadlift or good
morning or back extension or reverse
hyper. These make for excellent exercise
to throw in at the end. They don't beat
you up much. What I love about the
kickback, it matches the strength curve
of the hip extensors. So the hips are
about two and a half times stronger in
deep hip flexion compared to full hip
extension. And if you look at the moment
arm of this exercise, it's probably
around two and a half times longer in
the full stretch position than in the
full squeeze position. So it really
matches our strength curve to where it's
kind of hard throughout the entire range
of motion. The blue circle. And so when
it comes to exercises that hit that
posterior chain, both the hamstrings and
the glutes, the RDL and its many
variations are always going to find
their way on that list. However, when
we're looking for aesthetics or
athletics and we want to get the balance
that we might lack right now, splitting
up the legs one at a time is where we're
going to turn to the dumbbell single leg
RDL to accomplish that. And what I like
about this exercise is it does give me a
chance to either focus a little bit more
on the hamstrings by keeping the leg a
little straighter or a little bit more
on the glutes by allowing the knee to
bend more as I lean forward. So, if your
main pursuit was to grow bigger
hamstrings, the overloaded aspect of
this with the dumbbells will give you
that leg up. However, because the
balance might become your limiting
factor, it's not the best option for
you. So, it's going to get a ranking of
better but just not best yet. We have
better options coming. Totally agree
with everything he said there, but
that's why we do braced single leg RDL's
or you can do them off the Smith machine
or the hammer strength deadlift like a
plate loaded device for more stability
because I agree and if you don't have
anything to brace onto, you can do Bands
because yeah, these really lack
stability and it impairs your ability to
maximally fire the muscle. Now, I would
also argue with RDL's you do bend the
knee more. So, if you want to target the
hamstrings more, you do a stiff leg. I
don't call that an RDL. I call it a
stiff leg deadlift versus a Romanian.
Romanians, you are bending the knee more
to get more glute stretch. And so, with
that, I now get to break out my yellow
marker as we continue to work our way up
the charts. This time to the better
still category. And what I like to do
here is give you that next best option
that I just mentioned. And we're talking
about the single leg RDL. Well, let's
start doing it with a cable rather than
a dumbbell. Because what this does is it
gives us all the same benefits we just
talked about with more stability. Why?
Because the cable actually gives us more
control in the frontal plane. What I
mean is if you held that dumbbell in
your hand, it can kind of float in all
three directions. But with the cable,
you're actually controlling that side to
side frontal plane motion a little bit,
which actually lends additional balance
to you, which takes that exercise that
was supposed to be driving those glute
and hamstring gains and actually allows
it to do so without having your balance
undercut you, so it gets the first in
the better still category. I have no
problem doing that with a cable, but I
still would want that cable to be
vertically loaded. What he did there was
he made it an angle, which changes the
vector, and now it becomes kind of more
horizontalish. does not require as much
hip extension torque in the stretch
position. It requires more hip extension
torque at end range in the squeeze. But
in my opinion, you shouldn't try to turn
an RDL into a squeeze exercise. You do
squats, lunges, split squats, step-ups,
Romanian deadlifts, and leg presses for
the stretch. You do kickbacks, 45
hypers, reverse hypers, hip thrust, and
glute bridges for the squeeze position.
You don't necessarily try to make
squeeze exercises stretch movements. and
you don't try to make stretch movements,
squeeze movements because you just do
them both separately and they perfectly
complement each other. That's my take.
And so I promised you I wouldn't bury
the hamstring curl altogether that I'd
give you a better option. Well, all you
have to do is change the way you perform
the exercise. And this is sitting on
your butt. That's right. A seated
hamstring curl is a much better option.
Why? Because we're fixing all the things
we saw wrong with the earlier versions.
And you can see that when you perform
the exercise from this position, your
knees and thighs actually go down
towards hip extension rather than into
hip flexion as you bring your knees
back. And what's good about this is you
still get the ability to grow those
hamstrings through isolated knee flexion
and overload. But we don't have to have
that negative side effect that came by
just being in the opposite prone
position where our knees driving into
hip flexion. All those low back pains go
away, but the gains are actually here.
So, I agree the seated hamstring curl is
amazing for hamstring growth, but the
way he was performing it, I want to see
that full stretch at the top. In fact,
if you have good hamstring flex, I want
to see the L position. The bottom
position, I want to see straight legs,
an upright torso, I want it to be an L.
And if you have even better hamstring
flexibility than that, in fact, you can
lean forward even more. But I want full
knee extension at the top of the
movement, get that full stretch, and
that's what's going to grow the hammies
the most. So, in that example, who's
missing out on like the top 15, 20° of
knee extension to maximize the stretch
torque on the hammies? Much better
alternative for those looking to use a
machine. And speaking of improvements,
let's keep them coming. Instead of doing
those heel presses or even the standing
cuff kickbacks, you have another option
here. It's the banded step through. And
what you'll notice about this exercise
is that it gives you more range of
motion. So, therefore, more resistance
through hip extension, making it a
better exercise. And once again, the
bands will give you the opportunity to
progressively overload to a higher
resistance band, which will continue to
allow you to progress the exercise as
needed. Now, this is one that I like to
use with my athletes, not just because
of what I just spoke about, but also
because it tends to help you as a
mobility drill to get into deeper and
deeper hip flexion. There's a lot of
good to say about this, and it's
certainly the best variation we've
talked about so far to accomplish the
same thing. So the band is step through
again. Okay. I've never seen anyone do
that exercise before, but I don't think
you get a lot of length change
throughout the band just because of the
band being overhead. As it moves, it's
not going to get much stretch. So I
don't agree with that being an awesome
exercise. But that step through motion
can be done with a high pulley position
with a cable column. So you can do cable
kickbacks that way. You can also kind of
do that with the assisted chin-up
machine. You can't get full hip
extension on it, but you can kind of
load that step down motion. I like that.
Most bros would say that exercise sucks.
They'd say just do step-ups. I actually
really like that exercise, but now
they're making machines like Max Pump
makes a machine. I don't I haven't tried
it. Glute equipment is on the rise.
People are making crazy machines now.
You got Max Pump, you got glute builder,
you got booty builder. So yeah, I don't
agree with Jeff about that being
awesome, but I do like that motion and
theoretically it's an amazing way to
train the glutes. If you can provide
tension throughout the entire range of
motion, the yellow circle. Now, if the
criteria for this list was to choose
exercises that were capable of driving
high levels of conditioning and power,
then this next one would be way at the
top of the list, but it's not. So, it
falls here. We're talking about the
kettle bell swing. Now, this exercise is
one of the best ways to train the glutes
and to do so explosively, but it also
almost automatically guarantees that you
learn to hinge properly. And the hinge
is the foundation of glute activation.
If we can learn to hinge properly at the
hips, then we can engage the glutes at
the right time and learn to ultimately
recruit them and grow them better. Now,
the limitation is often times the load
that we use here. Unless you have access
to a very heavy kettle bell or one
that's challenging for you, you're not
going to find the ability to overload
this enough to keep the gains coming
once you've reached a certain point, but
it certainly is an amazing exercise and
one that deserves a spot here up high on
the list in the last one in the better
still category. And so now I get to
break out my Cbell swings. I so agree
with Jeff on this. It's not the best
hypertrophy exercise. But if you give me
someone to train and they're proficient
in kettle bell swings, then I'm going to
have the easiest job as a trainer
teaching them squats, Romanian
deadlifts, hip thrusts. It's crazy cuz
swings are hard to master. But if you do
swings early on in your career, for
example, back in the day, RKC was really
popular. Whenever I'd get someone who
was like RKC certified, their form was
amazing on everything. So it's kind of
like I wish more people spent time early
in their career learning swings. It just
seems to build a really good movement
foundation. But back in the day, I had a
2003 pound kettle bon. In fact, I I feel
like I was the first one to ever get it.
I ordered off Amazon. I remember the
shipping was so expensive. This was like
2012. This was like 13 years ago. And
yeah, I could swing that thing for like
20 reps. And I can't tell you how
freaking hard it is to swing a 203 lb
kettle bell 20 reps. I even wrote an
article for Teenation back in the day.
Are heavy Cbell swings better than
dynamic effort deadlifts? Meaning like
powerlifters do explosive deadlifts. I
think they should be doing heavy swings.
They're harder and they're harder
through the full range. But now I've
come to believe that neither one are
that good for powerlifters. I think you
should air on the side of more
specificity and just do more volume with
lower RP or more RI. Powerlifters lately
are doing way better by doing more
volume but not pushing it so hard on
their sets, leaving more reps in the
tank, not taking sets to failure. So
they're lasting longer and they're
performing better. Back in the day,
everything was to failure. But I
digress. Kbell swings great for building
movement competency. Not the best for
hypertrophy because it's an explosive
lift. And to maximize tension on the
muscle, you ultimately need to grind out
those last few reps and you need slower
muscle contractions. In order to
maximize hypertrophy, owing to the force
velocity relationship, that's how you
get maximum tension. which is why I like
hip thrust more than kettle bell swings
because the hip thrust is kind of like a
kettle bell swing with just heavier
loading and the ability to grind it out.
So, agree with Jeff there. Green marker
is we continue to work our way all the
way up to the top, but we're stopping
just short here in the almost best
category. And the place we're going to
start is with an improvement on those
kettle bell swings. We're talking about
the pull through. Now, once again, we
have a groundbased exercise like the
kettle bell swing, which I like. But we
also get a chance to load this a little
bit more heavily because we have the
option to just move that pin up the
weight stack more and more to
accommodate our increasing strength
gains and ultimately size gains. Now, I
also like the fact that this is once
again reinforcing all the good things
about the swing through that hip hinge
overload. And what's nice about this
exercise is often times for people when
you remove the speed component of the
kettle bell swing, they have a much
easier time getting to a good glute
contraction, which ultimately is going
to drive the hypertrophy you're looking
for. So for me, the pullthrough gets the
first green circle in the almost best
category. I started doing pullthroughs
in I think like 2009 and I quickly could
do the whole stack and then I was
pinning 45s to the stack. I remember
pinning a 100 lb plate to the stack. I'd
have to lean forward so much to not it
just it was ugly. Okay, so really strong
people, you almost overcome the ability
to perform pullthroughs because your
hipic sensor gets so strong. You can't
stay put. It would tip you backwards.
That being said, here in Gloot Lab San
Diego, we got really creative. We would
wear a belt connected to a cable column.
We would hold on to like sled handles or
even partners holding your hands and
we'd do that motion. We'd even do it
kneeling to take the hammies out of it.
We do kneeling with bands. We do them
with cables. We do them braced for
maximum stability. That was a staple for
a while and then we just gave up on it.
But side tangent, it's 2020 COVID
quarantine. One of my star clients,
Booty Brie, Briana Alexander, she had a
roommate that was immuno compromised.
So, no one was allowed to leave the
house and she couldn't come to Glute
Lab. So, I would load up my truck and
come to her and train her in her
driveway and and just not make contact.
And this really happened. I gave her
band kneeling hip thrusts and she was
doing them and a FedEx driver comes by
and delivers a package and he sees
Briana like humping against the band
resistance and he just takes off and he
broke out into a sprint and ran into his
truck and like squealled his tires out
of there. He must have thought we were
doing something naughty. We looked at
each other and just died laughing
because what did he think we were doing?
But yeah, that was popular for a time
and then it kind of vanished. I do like
band kneeling hip thrusts when you can
hold on to something. It's so stable.
Some people love them, some people
don't. Just like kneeling squats. Some
people love them, some people don't. But
back to pullthroughs. I like them for
pregnant women. They love them. I never
bash exercises too much. But in my
opinion, it's like why do a pullthrough
when you can do a hip thrust? It's more
stable. You get greater loading. That
doesn't mean I don't allow them in my
gym. If someone likes them, have at him.
Throw them in at the end. But once he
gets strong, it's just not enough. I
like that Jeff thinks for himself and
doesn't just fall on the bandwagon, but
I just don't think pullthroughs are that
good. To me, this next exercise is one
that's way too often underutilized, but
one that we use often with our athletes,
and it's the dumbbell leaning forward
stepup. And what's great about this
movement is you can easily load it
depending upon the weight of the
dumbbells that you grab. But what's nice
is just by changing the orientation of
your body prior to starting the
exercise, you can shift the load more
from the quads to the glutes and
hamstrings. So, we just assume this
forward tilt of our torso before we
start the ascent on every rep. So, what
this does is it just preloads the
glutes. So, now as I press down through
my foot and drive myself up and get as
close as I can to full hip extension and
I even have that good eccentric loading
on the way back down again, I can train
one leg at a time to overcome those
muscle imbalances and weaknesses. It's
going to get another green circle here
in the almost best category. I love that
step-up variation that he showed, the
glute dominant step-up. Love it. I do
think some people would be unstable with
it, especially when you use really,
really heavy loads. If you're shorter,
you can actually do step-ups off the
Smith machine. You can do zer step-ups.
No one ever does them, but they're more
stable. And if you can't do it, you
could just dump the bar forward. But
like, but yeah, dumbbells, you can lose
your balance. So, I like braced, but the
problem is you can get too strong when
you're doing braced. You hold on to
something for stability and you have
dumbbell loading in one arm. You can get
too strong for that to where what's the
heaviest dumbbell most gyms? 100 lb. You
know, a lot of my girls could do 100 lb
step-ups. We did high step-ups a little
more upright cuz you get more stretch.
But then I realized, no, you don't have
a lot of torque loading compared to when
you just go to parallel and lean forward
more. So now we do step-ups like that.
In fact, this reel I made on Instagram
was one of my most popular reels I've
ever made on why we switch from doing
step-ups like this to this. And I
remember it got me like over 12,000
followers from that one reel. After
that, every influencer I saw switched to
doing step-ups like that. It was
probably one of the most influential
reels ever made because that marked the
beginning of every influencer doing
step-ups in a glute dominant fashion.
So, I like to see that Jeff was talking
about this a couple years ago. Kind of
ahead of the curve on this glute
dominant step-up. But, I do think
there's better ways to do it than what
he showed. Just trying to get a little
more stability. Now, also that being
said, I hate when people just act like
anything unstable sucks because now
we've gone to where everything has to be
Smith machine or plate loaded and they
act like you can't possibly get good at
a free weight exercise while still being
stable. And that's not true. If you've
trained people for decades, you know we
used to always just use free weights and
people didn't just fall over all the
time. You get coordinated, you get good
at things with free weights. And so I
mentioned before that the glutes and
hamstrings prefer to work together. If
we had an exercise that allowed us to
overload and resist knee flexion and
also hip extension, then we would have a
great exercise. Well, this pair of
exercises actually allows you to do just
that. And regardless of whether you have
access to the equipment, you're going to
have an option to do it. And we're
talking about either the glute ham raise
or the slick floor bridge curl. And what
you can see here is again that
coordinated effort between the glutes
and hamstrings. On the glute ham raise,
you get that initial contraction from
the glutes to stabilize the pelvis and
assist in the driving of the whole body
up into this knee flex position. And of
course, this is a tremendous overload on
the hamstrings. And we could actually
increase the load here as we want to by
simply adding additional plate if
needed. But let's say you didn't have
access to this machinery. Well, you can
do what I always show here. It's a slick
floor bridge curl. And this is a
bodyweight variation. And it's a lot
harder than it looks. You're basically
doing the same thing here. You're
starting with a glute bridge through
good hip extension, maintaining that
throughout, and then actively and
dynamically using your hamstrings to
curl your legs in and back out. A good
eccentric overload here, too. The key,
as always, is to keep your glutes
really, really high while you're moving
your feet back and forth. And even here,
if you want an additional overload, try
to do this one leg at a time. It is not
easy. Either way, you're getting that
holy grail, that good combination of the
activation of both those muscle groups
together. And therefore, 12 years ago, I
wrote an article for Teenage Gutting the
glute ham raise. And I said, you put
glute in the name and people think your
glutes are working. It's a hamstring
exercise. The knee flexion torque so far
exceeds the hip extension torque,
especially when you factor in their
maximum capabilities. Like our hip
extensors are freakishly strong. All
they're doing in a glute ham raise is
keeping your torso level. It's really a
knee flexion hamstring movement. But if
I was doing glute ham raises, I would
put the foot position way higher. In
fact, you want the feet a little higher.
so that the shins are horizontal when
you get to the bottom of the movement.
And in my opinion, you just want to come
to parallel or a little bit below. And
then the slick floor bridge curls. It's
funny, I never prescribed those ever.
But during that quarantine, people
needed body weight exercise. Well,
that's really like one of the few
hamstring exercise you can do from home
with no equipment. So, my Booty Bub
Brett members probably got really sick
of hearing about these as an option, but
I had to cater to people training from
home during that period. So, those are
great exercises. I actually like them so
much I invented a hamstring track for
the hammock and roller. My buddy Bert
Saurin from Saurinx invented the glute
ham roller. I invented the track for it.
So, combined together, you got this
super stable exercise. It's so good. You
can do hamstring curls on flat ground
and when you get really good, you can do
them with your torso elevated on a
bench. This is so hard to do. I can
barely do them with two legs, but I have
clients who can do it with one leg with
freakishly strong hammies. All right,
let's move on before it gets that big
green circle in our almost best
category. And so, as we've done here a
few times on this list already, we've
made the improvements and now we're
going to make that ultimate improvement
when it comes to the RDL. So, instead of
the single leg variations, we can now
move towards the classic barbell RDL.
And with good reason, because if you're
pretty confident that you don't have any
of those underlying left to right
imbalances, then this is going to give
you the best chance to overload the
exercise and create the most growth in
both the hamstrings and the glutes. And
again, with a lot more stability since
you're not in any single leg balance
situation. An additional plus for the
exercise is it's a good accessory
movement to help you if you struggle at
all with that end range of a deadlift.
It just has a lot of utility here and
it's one of the best exercises you can
do for the posterior chain. It has to be
on this list and it has to be somewhere
at the very top. It's funny. RDL's have
gotten so popular. I feel like they're
more popular than deadlifts now. Like
really, Romanians are the most popular
deadlift variation in in existence right
now. They're more popular than sumo,
more popular than conventional, more
popular than trap bar. You almost never
hear of trap bar deadlifts anymore. It's
kind of funny when you've been around
for decades to see the trends. But the
RDL is such an amazing glute exercise
and there's so many good ways to do it
with the barbell. I like doing it off
the pit shark or off a belt squat
apparatus. There's so many good single
leg RDL variations. My favorite being
single leg abducted or hip supported.
But with the RDL, I've even changed the
way I teach the RDL to where I will
allow the knees to go forward a little
bit. So you have a little bit of forward
shin angle, some forward knee migration,
and that allows you to get a deeper
stretch on the glutes. So, if you're
like me and you feel all hamstrings in a
typical RDL, move your knees forward
just a little bit at the onset of the
exercise and then move back and you'll
feel even more in the glutes and less in
the hammies. But I totally agree with
it, Jeff here. The RDL is one of the
best glute exercises in existence. Let's
see what he picks for number one. The
almost best category. And so, any good
list of leg exercises wouldn't be good
if it didn't have some variation of a
squat on it. For us, it's going to be
the low bar variation. And there's a
reason for this. Because it sets your
body up to recruit the posterior chain
muscles more effectively. By simply
carrying the bar lower on those lower
rear delts, you're going to have to
pitch your torso forward at a bit of an
angle. What this does, as I've mentioned
before, is it recruits those posterior
chain muscles more effectively, and it
carries through as you go down into the
bottom portion of the squat, allowing
you to more effectively drive out of the
squat and also handle heavier loads. The
progressive overload was never in doubt
here, nor was its placement at some
point on this list. Ultimately, here way
up high, the low bar squat is going to
be the last in the almost best category.
Okay, I love to see low bar squats. A
lot of women don't like low bar. They
like high bar, but most bros like low
bar, but yeah, lean forward, sit way
back. Coming up in strength and
conditioning, everyone used to think the
squat had to be so upright, and if you
lean forward at all, you get criticized
on social media by everyone. And now I'm
very glad to see that the forward lean
has become accepted. And now we have a
consensus that it works more glute. I
think going to parallel doing low bar
and leaning forward a ton and keeping
the shins pretty vertical. Even using a
box squat if you can so you reach the
same depth every rep is the best way to
squat for glute growth. In fact, I love
the same on an angled Smith machine too.
I like it even more. The angled Smith
machine lowar glute dominant squat is
probably my favorite way to squat for
glute development. And then second being
with the BCT bell standing on blocks
leaning forward like that. It's so
smooth and I'm glad Jeff included a
squat variation on here because squats
are legendary for building the glutes.
So agree with Jeff there. Let's see what
he picks for number one. Some of you
might be thinking, but what about some
of the other exercises that Jeff has
shown in the past that have been very
very helpful? Well, I would consider
those corrective exercises either done
for neuromuscular activation or to
overcome a glute medius weakness or some
sort of hip imbalance. they wouldn't
necessarily find a home on this list
when we're talking about hypertrophy and
growth. However, stay tuned. That one's
coming. That's kind of cool to see those
exercises he's shown. And so, that
leaves us with only one. And of course,
there can only be one when it comes to
the best of the best. You weren't
looking over my shoulder the whole time,
were you? Whether it's a surprise or
not, we're talking about the barbell hip
thrust. And this exercise simply checks
all the boxes when it comes to glute
development. Yes, you can progressively
overload it very easily. Yes, you can
perform it safely. And yes, it's going
to provide the muscle hypertrophy that
you're looking for. Or as Jesse said,
it's going to help you grow that juicy
booty. Ooh la la. The reason why this
exercise sits way up here at the top,
even above our beloved squat, is because
muscle activation studies will prove how
much more superior this is when it comes
to recruiting the glutes on any
exercise. Throw in the fact that the
resistance curve here is superior as
well, ensuring that we have a heavy load
placed on those glutes in peak
contraction. Guys, this is just the best
exercise when it comes to delivering the
gains that you really want. and it also
has those hamstring isometric benefits
built in as well. This is going to get
that green star as the best of the best
in our glute exercise rankings. I love
that Jeff ranked the hip thrust as the
number one glute builder. Obviously, I
agree with him, but I'm biased. I'm the
inventor of the exercise. Jeff, get a
bar pad. Jesus, that poor guy. Here's
what we've learned since then with the
Plotkins study. Yes, it has higher EMG
activity, but it tied squats for glute
growth. Even though they have higher
glute activation than squats, the squat
stretches you more and has more torque
in the stretch. So theoretically, the
squat would be better because of the
better glute stretch and the more torque
in the stretch position. But the hip
thrust is so damn amazing. It's so damn
hard in the full squeeze position. It
produces so much active force that it
compensates for those two things. And
that's why you got the same glute
growth. In fact, glute growth was a
little bit higher, just slightly higher
for the hip thrust group. It wasn't
statistically significant, but everyone
knows you can perform way more volume
with hip thrust than you can squats.
Like, if I did my maximum volume on
squats per week, I'm sure I could
probably do eight hard sets a week for
squats. Anything more than that, I would
start I would get injured eventually. I
would start to spin my wheels. But hip
does I could probably do 24 sets to be
honest. I could probably do eight sets
three times a week if I wanted to and
recover just fine because they just
don't beat you up that much. They work
you at shorter muscle lengths so you
don't create the muscle damage. So your
body doesn't have to expend energy
repairing damage. It can go straight to
building muscle and hypertrophy rather
than regeneration. And it doesn't beat
you up systemically. You don't feel
wiped out the next day. It doesn't lead
to nearly as many injuries as like
squats or deadlifts. But obviously, I
think you should do both. You should do
a stretch position movement and a
squeeze position movement. And there's
so many good ways to hip thrust. You've
got the barbell like he showed. You got
the Smith machine. And now you have all
these plate loaded devices and even
selectorized devices from all the
manufacturers. You got BC Strength
Thruster Pro, which I think is the best
plate loaded device. You've got Hammer
Strength, which is second best. You've
got Booty Builder. You've got Glute
Builder, and all the other companies are
making them, too. I'm loving the fact
that we don't have to set up the barbell
all the time anymore. We can just hop on
a machine. So, if you're looking for
quads, that's coming soon. If you're
looking for a chest or shoulders rank
video, you can find them here. And also,
if you're looking for a complete
program, you can get them over at
athletics.com. Guys, click subscribe so
you never miss a video when we put one
out. See you soon. I'm gonna conclude
this video by saying, Jeff, that was
awesome. You got to listen to all the
experts and hear their rationale, and
you'll absorb some of the stuff from
everyone. I've been listening to all the
experts since the '9s. You know, I've
never felt like I'm above learning from
people. So, I enjoyed hearing Jeff's
thoughts on these different exercises.
And I also think it's really unfair to
react to something that someone did a
couple years ago. But I'm trying to
resurrect my YouTube channel. I know
Jeff's thoughts have changed in the last
couple years. If someone reacted to a
video I did a couple years ago, I'd be
pissed. I'd be like, "Dude, we didn't
even have half of this research that we
have now." So, Jeff, I'm sorry. I did
you dirty there. If you're not following
Jeff, definitely do so. He's a legend.
Like I said, he has more followers than
anyone in the game. He's a YouTube
pioneer. Jeff, thank you for providing
me with the opportunity to share my
knowledge. And to my followers, if you
like this stuff, let me know in the
comments because I'll try my best to
keep doing it, keep reacting to people's
videos, or do you just want me focusing
on my own topics? Let me know in the
comments. Make sure to give me a follow
and please make sure to hit like if you
like what you saw. I'm Brett Conturus,
aka the glute guy.